<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Roma ruens. Dagon falling before the Arke, or, The glory of Christ over-shadowing all other glories. / As it was delivered in a sermon before. the right Honourable Lord Major, and the right worshipful aldermen his brethren, at Mercers Chappel. By Nicholas Rust, chaplaine to the right Honourable Lord Major. Magna veritas &amp; prævalet.</title>
            <author>Rust, Nicholas, b. 1617 or 18.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92134</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2369</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E597_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206294</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865468</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865468</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117709</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92134)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117709)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 92:E597[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Roma ruens. Dagon falling before the Arke, or, The glory of Christ over-shadowing all other glories. / As it was delivered in a sermon before. the right Honourable Lord Major, and the right worshipful aldermen his brethren, at Mercers Chappel. By Nicholas Rust, chaplaine to the right Honourable Lord Major. Magna veritas &amp; prævalet.</title>
                  <author>Rust, Nicholas, b. 1617 or 18.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 17, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at the Black-spread-Eagle at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.L. [1650]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill. 2. 1649".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117709:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ROMA RUENS.</p>
            <p>Dagon falling before the Arke, OR, The Glory of Chriſt over-ſhadowing all other glories.</p>
            <p>As it was delivered in a Sermon before the Right Honourable Lord Major, and the Right Worſhipful Aldermen his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, at MERCERS CHAPPEL.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Nicholas Ruſt,</hi> Chaplaine to the Right Honourabl Lord Major.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Magna eſt veritas &amp; praevalet.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MAL. 3.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>But who may abide the day of his coming? and who ſhall ſtand when he appeareth? for he is like a refiners fire, and like fullers ſope.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Black-ſpread-Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls. M.DC.L.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:117709:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117709:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable THOMAS FOOT, Lord Major of the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and the reſt of the Honourable Senatours of that Body.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N obedience to your commands, I here publiſh the ſubſtance of what I preſented before you at <hi>Mercers Chappel;</hi> otherwiſe I ſhould have been willing to have lyen dormant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exceeding conſciencious of mine own weakneſſe and inſufficiency,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> for though I cannot deny (but muſt confeſs to the praiſe of the Lords ſuper abundant grace) that ſomething of the light and glory of the Goſpel in the face of Jeſus Christ, hath dawned upon my darke heart; yet this I know, that the candle of the Lord cannot burn with a more dim light then in my ſelf, for although truth (in ſome meaſure) liveth in me, yet clouds and darkeneſſe are round about it: So that I have but little of the ſpirit in abundance of infirmity of the fleſh, yet truth is powerful though I be weake, and the glory of it doth out-ſhine all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther glories, though in the meanest inſtrument: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any of the glory of Chriſt breake forth in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.28.</note> let him have the glory who hath choſen the weak things of the world to confound the mighty.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:117709:3"/>
            <p>Honourable Senatours, God hath made you inſtruments to make this City a quiet habitation for his people, and to lay a reſtraint on thoſe that would moleſt and vex them: we take it kindly,<note place="margin">Math. 25.40.</note> yea Jeſus Chriſt doth take it kindly at your hands, that you will allow his Saints, to have a place to reſt their heads on under your Juriſdiction: we wiſh you well in the name of the Lord, and our God continue your hearts, in this love unto his Peculiar inheritance, for you muſt be comforted by the ſpirit of Chriſt in all your ſorrows and counſelled by it in all your ſtreights,<note place="margin">John 14.26.</note> and aſſiſted by it in all the difficult affaires of the Sate, therefore you do well to indulge love and tender that ſpirit though in thoſe who are very contemptible in the eye of the world,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.28. Rom. 13.1.</note> and not to hearken to ſuch who would have the powers that are of God engaged againſt God. Honourable Senatours: God hath called you unto places of eminencie, &amp; committed a great people to your charge, and truly you need more then the wiſedome of Man to manage ſuch a truſt.</p>
            <p>But he who called <hi>Peter</hi> forth to walk upon the waters (ſaying come) gave him that power,<note place="margin">Math. 14.29. 2 Cor. 12.10.</note> whereby he was ſupported on the waters: therefore never fear to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage for God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2 Cor. 1.5.</hi> Sicut abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant paſſiones Chriſti, ſic a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> if ye have a call from God: for the more oppoſitions ye meet withall, the more encouragements, and divine aſſiſtances ſhall come from God, to carrie you through ſuch difficulties and oppoſitions. You have had plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull experince hereof: for even to admiration God hath appeared for you, in the mount he hath been ſeen, and in the maidſt of all theſe ſtorms, you and your Relations have been under the protection of our Redeemer: yea the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, hath ſtood round about your City, ſo that your enemies rock hath not been as your rock, themſelves being witneſſes. Oh how are ye engaged to the God of
<pb facs="tcp:117709:3"/>your ſalvation, who hath not given you victories to make your ſelves great,<note place="margin">Iſaiah 58.6. Pſal. 144 14 Iſa iah 58.12.</note> or to exalt your own intereſt by them: but to exalt his name, in removing every heavie burden and letting the oppreſſed goe free, that there might be no complaining in your streets. Then you ſhall be stiled the Repairers of our breaches, the Restorers of the paths to dwel in, and the bleſſings of many,<note place="margin">difficilima quae pulchra.</note> who are ready to periſh would come upon you. I know (noble Sanatours) that in the proſecution of truth, juſtice, and righteouſneſſe,<note place="margin">Si Deus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſcum quis longa nos. <hi>1 Pet 4.</hi> ult</note> you will meet with many adverſaries: yet who can harme you while God ſtands by you to keep all your bones? Oh both in doing, and ſuffering commit your ſelves, your bodies and ſouls to him, as unto a faithfull preſerver:<note place="margin">Pſal. 23. Exoe 33, 14.</note> Oh Remember how the glorious preſence of the Lord of hoſts hath gone along with your Armies ſtep by ſtep: that through <hi>Europe</hi> you have been famous for the preſence of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst you; therefore fear nothing, but the withdraw ment of that bleſſed preſence: for while it doth continue with you,<note place="margin">Joſhewa 2.9.</note> you will be formidable to all the Nations round about you, and the Majestie of heaven with you, and for you, will attract and draw forth the envie, and indignation of the Nations against you: (who are very angry, and their wrath is come) but Sanctifie the Lord in your hearts,<note place="margin">Revel. 11.18. Pſal. 3.6. Rom. 8.</note> and make him your fear: and then you may bid defiance to them, and the worst that they can do; for though ye had Nations, Kings, and Kingdomes, for your adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, yet God would eſtabliſh you:<note place="margin">Eſay. 54. verſ. 14. John. 10.29.</note> for the Lion of the tribe of <hi>Juda,</hi> who doth defend, and ſave us, is ſtronger then the roaring Lion, who ſeeketh to devour us: In your povertie, and weakneſſe,<note place="margin">Exodus. 14.13.</note> your eies have ſeen the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of God: Oh therefore do not decline, and Bauke, the cauſe of Chriſt, and his people, if itſhould be low,
<pb facs="tcp:117709:4"/>and deſperate (in humane probabilities) you would ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly loſe your glory, and become ſo weake, impotent, and contemptible, if you ſhould deſert the power of God, and ſeeke to fortifie your ſelves, with the arm of fleſh: that all humane dependencies ſhould not ſupport you. Straglers are taken by the enemy, when thoſe ſouldiers that follow their Captains, &amp; ſtand to their Colers, are ſafe. Look up to <hi>Jeſus,</hi> the Author &amp; finiſher of your faith,<note place="margin">Heb: 17.1. Heb. 2. Epheſ. 6.14.</note> keep cloſe to the Captain of your Salvation. Buckle on your harneſſe, gird the ſword of the ſpirit about your loines, and take unto you the Helmet of ſalvation, and the breſtplate of righteouſneſſe, and follow him,<note place="margin">Rvel. 19.13.</note> who ſitteth upon a white horſe, cloathed in a vesture dipt in the blood of his ſufferings, (whoſe name is the word of God) and ye will ſay that there is no glory, like unto this glory: for it will continue with you, when all other glorie ſhall be over-ſhadowed, and out-ſhined. Thus (deſiring pardon for my boldneſſe) I commit and commend ye all, your City, families, friends, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, to the grace, and goodneſſe, of our Redeemer.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your dayly Oratour at the Throne of grace NICH. RUST.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117709:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Marke 9.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And there was a cloud that overſhadowed them: and a voice came out of the cloud, ſaying, This is my beloved Son: hear him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the beginning of this Chapter,<note place="margin">Verſe <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> Jeſus taketh with him <hi>Peter, James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> and went up into a high mountaine to pray (as <hi>Luke</hi> hath it) for when we are to wait on God in ſuch an ordinance,<note place="margin">Lukke 9.28.</note> we are to get into a mountaine (that is) to be above the world; for you read that Chriſt ſent the multitude away when he was (thus) to converſe with his Father,<note place="margin">Mat. 14.23.</note> ſo are we, to diſmiſſe the multitude of earthly thoughts and cares, that we may attend upon the Lord in ſuch a duty without diſtraction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith, that as Chriſt prayed,<note place="margin">Luke 9.29.</note> the faſhion of his countenance was altered, and his raiment was white and gliſtering: For the Lord leaveth ſome impreſſions of his own glory upon thoſe that come to have communion with himſelf in thoſe ordinances wherein he meets their ſoules.<note place="margin">Exod. 34.30.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> face did ſhine
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117709:5"/>when he had been with God upon the mount. Oh 'tis good to draw neer to God.<note place="margin">Pſal. 73. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>But aſſoon as Chriſt appeared:<note place="margin">Verſe <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared with him in glory. By <hi>Moſes,</hi> I do not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the perſon of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but the miniſtration of <hi>Moſes</hi> ſo far as it was <hi>Elementarie &amp; typicall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.1.</note> a ſhadow of things to come, and ſo to be overſhadowed, a glory which was to be outſhined by the glory of Chriſt. And by <hi>Elias,</hi> I do not underſtand the perſon of <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt (who was <hi>Elias</hi>) but his miniſtration, ſo far as it was the Baptiſme of water,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. John 3.30.</note> an outward ſign of the Baptiſme of Chriſt, a glory which was to be eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the glory of Chriſt: I muſt decreaſe, but he muſt increaſe. Now theſe two miniſters (being put for the miniſtrations themſelves) appeared with Chriſt: for whenſoever Chriſt exalts his glory, other glories ſeeke to ſtand up in competition with it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter</hi> is ſo ſatisfied with the viſion of this glory, that he is content ta take up his everlaſting habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the mount: Maſter it is good to be here, and to build tabernacles not onely to Chriſt, but to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> alſo, for when creatures ſtand up in compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition with Chriſt, we are ready to attribute to them the glory of Chriſt, magnifying them as Co-adjutors and Concauſes with Chriſt,<note place="margin">Habak. 1.16.</note> Sacrificing to our nets, building tabernacles to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> as well as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But it is the deſign of the Father to honour Chriſt,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.9.</note> and to give him a name above every name, that every knee may bow to him, and all glory (below him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) abaſe it ſelfe before him; therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> ſhall not be able to indure the Luſter of Chriſts
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117709:5"/>appearing who is the bright morning ſtar; <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> are overſhadowed and darkened by Chriſt, their glory is extinguiſed: no glory remained but the glory of Chriſt: Jeſus was left alone. For while <hi>Peter</hi> thus ſpake: <hi>A cloud overſhadowed them, and a voice came out of the cloud, ſaying, this is &amp;c.</hi> From the words thus opened we may obſerve, That—</p>
            <p>The glory of Chriſt doth overſhadow and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine,<note place="margin">Doct.</note> all other glories; that ſtand up againſt it, or in competition with it.</p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaking of the light and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Chriſt which ſhould break forth in the time of the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Iſaiah 40.</note> diſcovereth the vanity of all fleſhly glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, how it ſhould wither, die and fade before this glory, at the 5 verſe. The glory of the Lord ſhall be revealed &amp;c. and at the 7 verſe. The graſſe wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth, the flower fadeth &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaw in a viſion one like the ſon of man,<note place="margin">Dan 7.14.</note> in his glory, Kingdome and dominion: and ſee there how the glory of thoſe great and powerfull Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archies did paſſe away and vaniſh before this glory (it would have grieved the heart of any Royalliſt to have ſeen it) for the Thrones were caſt down, verſe 9. Their glory utterly marred, their power quite broken, and all by a little ſtone cut out of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines without hands, verſe 26.<note place="margin">Dan. 2.34.</note> Their dominion is taken away; conſumed and deſtroyed to the end, for the hand-writing was gone forth againſt them, MENE MENE TEKEL EUPHARSIN. They were weighed in the ballance, and found light, and their Kingdomes were departed from them.<note place="margin">Dan. 5.25</note> The Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> in another place doth diſplay (moſt divinely)
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117709:6"/>the magnificence of this Tranſcendent glory,<note place="margin">Eſay 2.10.</note> and ſee how the lofty looks, high thoughts &amp; great imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men are humbled and brought down, verſe 10. Great and mighty ones hide themſelves in the duſt for feare of the Lord, and for the glory of his Majeſtie, yea, verſe 11. the lofty lookes of men ſhall be humbled, and the haughtines of men ſhall be bowed down: and the Lord alone ſhall be exalted in that day, the day of the Lord of Hoſts ſhall ſo be upon every one that is proud and lofty, that migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ones ſhal be caſt from their ſeats, and the ſtrongeſt oakes of <hi>Baſhan</hi> will not be able to ſtand againſt this mighty blaſt.</p>
            <p>When the Angel came down from heaven who lightened the earth with his glory,<note place="margin">Rev. 18.1.</note> down came <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> and all her glory,<note place="margin">Verſe 16, 17, 18, 19.</note> ſo bemoaned and lamented by her admirers and adorers: for in one hour ſo great laches came to nought, for the glory of the new <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> the City of God doth even ſwallow up the glory of creatures!<note place="margin">Rev 21.24.</note> The nations do bring their glory into it. Thus you ſee the glory of Chriſt doth overſhadow and outſhine &amp;c. But I ſhall no longer ſtay in Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, but come to particulars. Firſt the glory of the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt doth overſhadow the wiſdome of the world; ſo that it is confounded by it, when it ſtands up in competition or in conteſtation with it: for the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, learning,<note place="margin">Acts 6.9.</note> policie and ſophiſtrie of the world did ſtand up againſt (and conteſt with) the wiſdome of God in Steven; but they were all borne down by the Majeſtie and power of it; for the truth of God is powerful,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.16.</note> yea it is the power of God to ſalvation and cannot be reſiſted in the meaneſt and weakeſt inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117709:6"/>but it will bear all before it; the Libertines, Cyrenians, &amp; Alexandrians were not able to reſiſt the ſpirit whereby he ſpake,<note place="margin">Acts 6.10.</note> or with all humane abilities to maintaine diſpute againſt him, for the ſchool of tyrannie is too weak for the ſchool of Chriſt: The Lord Jeſus at twelve years old diſputed with the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, confounding them and amazing them with his queſtions and anſwers; ſo powerful was the wiſdom of God in the child Jeſus:<note place="margin">Luke 2.48.</note> Now this wiſdome of God (which dwelt in Chriſt) is in all the Saints, though in a leſſe meaſure, yet ſufficient to deal with powers and principalities,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.27.</note> for God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world to confound the wiſe, and weak things to confound the things which are mighty, and baſe things of the world, and things which are deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and things which are not, to bring to nought things that are, that ſo the power of God being ſeen in weak inſtruments, no fleſh might glory in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, for this treaſure is in earthen veſſels,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.7.</note> that the praiſe might be of God and not of men: Thus the glory of the wiſdome of Chriſt doth darken the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of humane wiſdome, for his glory doth overſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow all other glories.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The glory of Chriſts power doth over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadow and out-ſhine (that is) doth confound and bring to nothing the glory of all fleſhly power that ſtandeth up againſt it, or in competition with it,<note place="margin">Zach. 4.7.</note> ſee a glorious diſcovery of this in the Goſpel by Saint <hi>John, Judas</hi> cometh with a band of men and officers,<note place="margin">John 18.4.</note> with weapons, lanthorns and torches to apprehend the Lord of life and glory; but Chriſt meets them in the power and Majeſtie of the God-head in him, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117709:7"/>ſaid, <hi>whom ſeek ye?</hi> and they fell backward to the ground, notwithſtanding all their fleſhly and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſiſtances they could not ſtand before him; the power of the creature fell before the power of God in Chriſt: therefore no man could take away his life, he lay'd it down of himſelf.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Saul</hi> had nought but a creature-power to ſupport him, and his kingdome, in the abſence of the power of God, which was departed from him; ſee how deſolate his houſe was left, ſee how the glory of it did fade and die away, (as any form) wherein God hath appeared) doth periſh and come to nothing when God doth withdraw from it.) And though <hi>Saul</hi> did ſeek to fortifie himſelf with fleſhly power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the power of God with <hi>David,</hi> and to keep up his eſteem and honour in the hearts of his ſubjects, and to quicken in them an admiration of his greatnes (which he ſaw decaying) honour me good <hi>Samuel</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the people, but all was ineffectual; for to what purpoſe do we ſpice, embalme and preſerve a carcaſe when the life and ſpirit is gone out of it? oh how did his heart meditate terrour in the apprehenſion of the withdrawment of the divine preſence! his pulſe did beat very low, and a cold ſweat ſtood upon his limbs; yea, all the ſymptomes of a dying glory: oh what ſtrivings and ſtruglings for life! he ran to <hi>Ephraim,</hi> called to <hi>Aſſyria:</hi> to the World, to the Devil, to the Witch of <hi>Endor.</hi> Oh his ſad complaint! God is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from me, and the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> make war againſt me; but all theſe ſtruglings were but the laſt prongs and pangs: for his glory expired, and the glory of his houſe; the houſe of <hi>Saul</hi> waxed weaker and weaker,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117709:7"/>and the houſe of <hi>David</hi> ſtronger &amp; ſtronger; the power of God with <hi>David</hi> did ſwallow up the power of the creature which was with <hi>Saul,</hi> for the glory of Chriſt doth overſhadow and out-ſhine all other glories.</p>
            <p>But that you may ſee further proof of this, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay 14.11.</note> that that glorious power of Chriſt doth overſhadow and confound all other powers that exalt themſelves againſt it: caſt your eye upon that place in <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> where you read of the aſpiring Tower of <hi>Babel,</hi> lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up it ſelf, and ſeeking to over-top the power and kingdome of Chriſt, for Verſe 13. <hi>Thou haſt ſaid in thy heart, I will aſcend into heaven, I will exalt my ſelf above the ſtars of God;</hi> but this power that ſhoke king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and made the earth to tremble, is brought down; this high and lofty Tower doth tumble be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the power and glory of Chriſts Kingdome: Thy pompe is brought down to the grave, Verſe 11. <hi>How art thou fallen from heaven, O Lucifer?</hi> ſee how ſtrongly &amp; ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtably this power doth act even in a weak forme: there ſhall not any man be able to ſtand before thee, ſaid God to <hi>Joſhuah</hi> (that is) before my power and preſence with thee, for as I was with <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſh. 1.5.</note> ſo will I be with thee, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This power was very dreadful when the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> cryed out, let us flee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Sam. 4.7.</hi> Deus venit in caſtra vae no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis vae nobis.</note> &amp;c. for God is come into the camp of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> who can ſtand before theſe mighty Gods? Theſe are the Gods which ſmote the <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> all the inhabitants of the Land did faint becauſe of the preſence and power of God with his people <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> for that power breaks all powers that daſh againſt it. The Kings of the earth, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.14.<note place="margin">Joh. 2 11.</note> make war againſt the Lamb, but he overcometh, for he is the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117709:8"/>Captaine of our Salvation, the moſt mighty, high and victorious King of kings,<note place="margin">Rev. 19.19.</note> and Lord of lords, and when the glory of his power breakes forth,<note place="margin">Mat. 1.24.</note> it over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadowes the glory of all other powers.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The glory of Chriſts rightouſneſſe doth overſhadow, darken and put out the glory of mans righteouſneſſe: The Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> before the revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the glory of Chriſts righteouſneſſe to his ſoul, did glory in his own righteouſneſſe,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and conformity to the Law, for he knew no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther name wherein he ſhould be ſaved; but thought his own workes muſt commend him unto God, and he eſteemed himſelf in his ſelf-righteouſneſſe, adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a glorious robe; but afterward upon the knowledge of Chriſt, it did appear a filthy rag, and it was a very loathing and abhorrence to his ſoul, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his legal priviledges and blameles wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings touching the Law,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> he counted all dung and droſſe in compariſon of Chriſt; for as ſoon as the Goſpel came, his ſin revived, his ſelf-righteouſneſſe died: that was crucified to him, and he to that, when the light of truth did ſhine into his heart, he was ſo overſhadowed with the glory of the Goſpel, that the glory of the Law was outſhined; for it was no glory in reſpect of that glory, vvhich vvas to be revealed.</p>
            <p>The righteouſneſſe of man is as an early devv, and as a morning cloud vvhich do paſs avvay, the devv and cloud vaniſh before the Sun,<note place="margin">Hoſan.</note> and the righteouſneſſe of man is confounded &amp; darkned by the Sun of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe; nothing doth ſo humble and abaſe the ſoul as the beholding this glory of Chriſts righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, nothing doth ſo diſcover to the ſoul its ovvn
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117709:8"/>unrighteouſneſſe, nor ſo pull down high thoughts and lofty imaginations in the heart, as to have a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the purity and righteouſneſs of God in Chriſt.<note place="margin">Job. 42.5.</note> I have heard of thee (ſaid <hi>Job</hi> of this Divine glory) but now mine eies ſee thee, wherefore I abhor my ſelf in duſt and aſhes. Oh how low doth the glory of Chriſt lay the glory of man! for when the glory of God appeared unto <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> he was ſo aſtoniſhed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded,<note place="margin">Iſay 6.5.</note> that he cries out, woe is me, I am undone, I have ſeen the Lord, I am a man of polluted lips; I am a ſinful man (ſaid <hi>Peter</hi> when he had ſeen the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus) nothing doth ſo manifeſt to the creature its em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptineſſe and inſufficiency, as a ſight of that eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and fulneſſe that is in Chriſt; then we ſee that we are nothing, that we have nothing, and can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing when the Lord diſcovereth himſelf to be all in all, for his glorious righteouſneſſe doth overſhadow and eclips the glory of all earthly righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The glory of Chriſts truth and worſhip doth quite blaſt and overſhadow the glory of mans worſhip, that is to ſay, a wil-worſhip according to the commandments of men: Oh how have we lived upon this worſhip, and fetched all our refreſhment from it! ſpeaking peace to our own ſouls, for the perfunctory and formal performance of any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar act of this worſhip,<note place="margin">Iſay 50. <hi>ult.</hi> 29.13.</note> though according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of men: But when that glorious Sun of Divine truth hath ariſen upon us, and cauſed his light and glory to dawne upon our darke hearts;<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.19.</note> this well of our former refreſhment, hath been utterly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted, we could no longer find comfort or ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in mens formalities; we might famiſh for any
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117709:9"/>ſoul-nouriſhment that we could find in them, they have appeared to us, ſo void of the preſence of Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Luke 24.5.</note> that we ſhould ſeek the living among the dead, to ſeek him there: ſo that the diſcovery of Chriſt in his truth, and Goſpel, hath diſovered the emptineſſe,<note place="margin">Iſay.</note> and deſtroyed the very being of thoſe things whereon we have lived: <hi>for the glory of Chriſt doth overſhadow all other glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Divine worſhip cannot but darken the glory of Wil-worſhip, for the truth of God muſt needs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome and vanquiſh the deviſed worſhip of men: many are the deviſes of men, but the councels of God muſt ſtand: the word is powerful for the ſubverſion of ſtrong-holds, and bringing down humane imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations: therefore this may comfort us in the middeſt of all the errours of the enemies wherein we live; truth ſhall get ground of errour, but errour ſhall not get ground of truth, for truth is armed from heaven againſt oppoſers: therefore we are reſolved in this cauſe of Chriſts, to put it to the utmoſt triall, which be ſtrongeſt, the lies and falſhoods of men, or the truth and Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt:<note place="margin">Heb. 1.</note> ſurely the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this glory will out-ſhine all other glories, for can darkneſſe ſtand before the light? if the day break the ſhadowes muſt flie away,<note place="margin">Cant. 4.6.</note> the Kingdome of the beaſt was ruined by the preaching of the Goſpel, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was full of darkneſſe; that kingdome is an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of darkneſſe,<note place="margin">Revel. 16.10.</note> and a cauſe of darkneſſe, brought forth by darkeneſſe,<note place="margin">Ex quibus na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcimur ex iiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem nutrimur. <hi>Luke 2.32. 2 Pet. 1.19. Rev 2.28.</hi>
               </note> ſupported by darkneſſe, it main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines darkneſſe, and is maintained by darkneſſe; now Chriſt is a light to lighten the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> a light ſhining in a darke place, the bright morning-ſtar,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117709:9"/>that very light and glory of the Father, which muſt needs be deſtructive to the kingdome of darkneſſe, which cannot abide the brightneſſe of his coming, for the luſtre of it is above all other glory.<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Yea further, Wil-worſhip is ſet forth (in way of compariſon) by wax which melteth before the fire: the doctrines and traditions of men melt and diſſolve, when the Sun of Goſpel-light and truth waxeth hot.<note place="margin">Rev. 9.2.</note> Wil-worſhip is the ſmoke of the bottomleſſe pit: now ſmoke doth vaniſh, clouds are ſcattered and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipated when the Sun ariſeth. Let God ariſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 68.1.</note> let truth break forth, and what ſhall be contrary to truth, and God, will be ſcattered: even as ſmoke vaniſheth, ſo it will be driven away, and as wax melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth at the fire, ſo it will periſh at the preſence of the truth of God: ſo that hay and ſtubble will not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the fire,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.12.</note> which muſt try every mans worke of what ſort it is. The Prophet <hi>Malachi</hi> ſaith of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mal. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>Who ſhall abide his coming, for his coming is as a refiners fire, and fullers ſoape:</hi> He alludeth to the cuſtome of the refiners of ſubterraneal treaſures, who by fire pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie the ſilver and gold ore, ſeparating the droſs from it: ſo this refiner, the Lord Jeſus, will cauſe all the droſſe of humane inventions in the worſhip of God to paſſe away, to go forth as that ſcum and filth which will not abide the purity of his coming; for no mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of humanity will endure the refiners fire: for the truth of God carrieth all before it, daſhing the brats of <hi>Babylon</hi> againſt the ſtones, breaking not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly her Idols of courſer materials, as of wood and ſtone, but even thoſe of purer matter, as of gold and ſilver and precious ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es;<note place="margin">Rev. 18.12.</note> dlſo vering not onely
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117709:10"/>the myſterie of iniquity in groſſe formes,<note place="margin">For the man of ſin hath various forms, and though he acteth in a new form, yet he is the old ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</note> but even that which is more ſpecious and ſpun with a finer thred, for the word of the Lord is quick and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſharper then a two-edged ſword &amp;c. Thus the glory of Chriſts truth and worſhip, doth overſhadow and put out the glory of al humane &amp; carnal ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: for the Angel which cometh down from heaven (with the everlaſting Goſpel) hath great power, and the earth is lightened with his glory.<note place="margin">Rev. 18.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, the glory of Chriſts promiſes and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of his will and councels do overſhadow and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine all the deviſes and wills of men (that is) the deviſes, councels, and wills of men are not able to ſtand before the will and councel of God;<note place="margin">Iſay 46.10, 11</note> for firſt, the promiſes and propheſies of God muſt be fulfilled, and muſt take place,<note place="margin">Iſay 14.24.</note> maugre all the actings, and conncels of men. Glorious things are propheſied of the Church of Chriſt, in time of the new Teſtament, that her foundations ſhall be laid with Saphirs, and Carbuncles,<note place="margin">Iſay 54.11.</note> her gates ſhall be made of Agats, and all her borders of pretious ſtones: all which are of high eſteeme, and value, with our <hi>Lapidaries</hi> that know the vertues of theſe ſtones: now the enemies of the Church of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Iſay 54.15.</note> gather together, to hinder this glorious worke, and to keep off the fulfilling of theſe bleſſed Propheſies; for they had rather ſee <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> ſtones,<note place="margin">Pſul. 102.14.</note> lie ſcattered in the duſt, then compact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, to become a holy temple in the Lord: but all their engagements are in vaine, for when they riſe up thus againſt the worke of God they fall;<note place="margin">Verſe 15.</note> when they gather together againſt it they are ſcattered;<note place="margin">Verſe 17.</note> and no weapon formed againſt this worke doth proſper; all theſe (ſaith God to <hi>Sion,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:117709:10"/>concerning the Churches adverſaries (ſhal gather to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againſt thee; but they ſhall fall for thy ſake, for God rebuketh Kings and Kingdomes for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſake; thus ye ſee when God doth worke,<note place="margin">Iſay 43.13.</note> none can let him: <hi>Tobiahs</hi> and <hi>Sanballats</hi> may ſcoffe at the wayes of God, and ſet themſelves againſt them:<note place="margin">Nehem. 4.1, 2.</note> But the Temple ſhall be built, for not a title of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and propheſies of God ſhall fall to the ground;<note place="margin">Mat. 24.35.</note> they ſhall be verified though all men be found lyers.</p>
            <p>Then ſecondly, the councels of God do even baffle, and confound the deviſes of men, therefore let them aſſociate, and they will be broken in peeces;<note place="margin">Iſay 8.9.</note> let them take councel, and it will come to nothing, for ſaith the holy Ghoſt, many are the deviſes of men but the councels of God ſhal ſtand:<note place="margin">Iſay 46.</note> for it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible they ſhould be fruſtrated, by all the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and policy of creatures. Oh man,<note place="margin">Non eſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium contra dominum. <hi>Rom. 9.</hi>
               </note> who art thou, that doſt contend, and conteſt with him that is mighty?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the deſignes of God, do bear before them even to the duſt, all the conſpiracies, and combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men and devils, againſt them. The deſign of God (in the ſecond <hi>Pſalm</hi>) is to exalt his ſonne,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.8.</note> and to give him a name above every name:<note place="margin">Phil. 2.</note> Now nothing doth more dethrone man, and take away the glory of all fleſh, then the ſetting this Crown of glory upon the head of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Iſay 40. Pſal. 2.1.</note> therefore (at the firſt verſe) <hi>The Heathens rage, and the Kings of the earth stand up, and take councel againſt the Lord and his Chriſt.</hi> But he that dwels in heaven doth laugh them to ſcorn, for they imagine a vaine thing, when they thinke to hinder the deſign of God from being carried on: now
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117709:11"/>this is the deſign of God,<note place="margin">Verſe 6.</note> even to ſet his Sonne upon the holy hill of <hi>Sion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the will of God doth fruſtrate all the wills of men,<note place="margin">Pſal. 46.3.</note> in the 46. <hi>Pſalm; men ſeeke to exalt themſelves, and their own wills, which is the ground of thoſe commotions there ſpoken of:</hi> but God writeh vanity upon all their endeavours: the will of none but God can take place.<note place="margin">Verſe 10. &amp; <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note> Beſtill (ſaith hee) and know that I am God, and I will be exalted in the earth.</p>
            <p>They fight,<note place="margin">Pſal. 46.6, 7, 8, 9.</note> war and contend even until they fill the world with combuſtions, and diſtractions, &amp; all to ſet up their own crooked will; but God exalts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and maketh them all come in and lick the duſt before him: Know that I am God. <hi>Verſe</hi> 10. Oh bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, from whence cometh wars and fightings?<note place="margin">James 4.1.</note> even from our luſts that war in our members: we luſt to have our own wills, and intereſt, ſet up and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced: Royalliſts would have their will, and way, elſe no peace: Papiſts alſo would have their will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip eſtabliſhed; and the little horne of the beaſt would have all the other hornes knocked off,<note place="margin">Dan. 7.8.</note> to ſet up it ſelf: well brethren, this is our comfort, in the middeſt of all theſe claſhings, no will but the will of God, ſhall, or can take place. Oh that we could ſee all theſe various workings, and contex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of providence, all tranſactions in our Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, as ſo many lines meeting in the will of the Lord: then we ſhould all ceaſe from tormenting our ſelves in the proſecution of our own wills,<note place="margin">Mat. 26. Verſe 39. Pſal. 37 7.</note> and lie down ſatisfied in the will of the Lord, as in the Centre of our reſt: Deare hearts, there is ſweet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:117709:11"/>
            <p>Thus much for the Confirmation of the Point, I now come to Uſe and Application.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If the glory of Chriſt doth overſhadow and outſhine all other &amp;c. then this will informe us why carnal hearts do ſo oppoſe the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, even becauſe it doth eclips and darken all natures glory.</p>
            <p>So that if you will allow creatures to riſe up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt and oppoſe that which is deſtructive to their beings, you muſt not wonder why natural men (who have their life and glory in fleſhly wiſdome, fleſhly ſtrength, and fleſhly righteouſneſſe) ſhould riſe up againſt the miniſtration of the Spirit and Goſpel, which doth ſo darken and put out all theſe. Nature you ſee (in all) doth ſeeke to preſerve it ſelfe, and to reſiſt whatſoever may procure her deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and annihilation, therefore nature in us doth quake at the thought of death. Oh beloved the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel in its glory, doth confound and annihilate all fleſhly excellencies; it doth cauſe their glory to fade and die; Therefore you may ceaſe your admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, why in City and Country there ſhould be ſo much enmity againſt Chriſt, his truth and Goſpel: Men that would exalt themſelves and be ſomething in the eſteem of their own parts and gifts, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in their own wiſdome, glory, ſtrength,<note place="margin">Gol. 3.11.</note> right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eouſneſſe, cannot but ſet themſelves againſt him who will be all in all.</p>
            <p>Firſt, you ſhall ſee how men that exalt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in an earthly glory, cannot bear nor brook the glory of Chriſts kingdome and Goſpel, their knees do ſmite one againſt another,<note place="margin">Dan. 3.5.</note> their thoughts are
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117709:12"/>troubled when many run to and fro,<note place="margin">Mat. 2.3.</note> and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is encreaſed, when many come to joyne unto the Lord, and to give up their names to Jeſus Chriſt; their hearts, I ſay, do meditate terrour, as if the Saints gathering together would be their ſcattering; as if their glory would be their ſhame: this did trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Herod,</hi> and thoſe tidings out of the North (in the book of <hi>Daniel</hi>) did perplex <hi>Babylon;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 11.44.</note> therefore <hi>Herod</hi> ſought to ſlay the child Jeſus; therefore the Kings of the earth made war againſt the Lamb,<note place="margin">Rev. 17.14.</note> before whom they thought the honour, pompe and dignity of their Kingdomes could not ſtand, and that is the reaſon why ſo many Princes and Rulers,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.2.</note> have ſo endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſuppreſſe the kingdome of Chriſt, and to hinder it from taking place in their Dominions: have any of the Rulers believed on him?</p>
            <p>Secondly, they who magnifie humane wiſdome and humane worſhip, how they ſet themſelves againſt the Lord and his Chriſt: the learned <hi>Greeks</hi> eſteemed the preaching of the Goſpel fooliſhneſſe; the learned Rabbies could not receive it, but oppoſe it; it did ſo confound the wiſdome of the wiſe,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.27.</note> and bring to nothing the underſtanding of the prudent: the ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of <hi>Diana</hi> filled the City of <hi>Epheſus</hi> with confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">Acts 19.27.</note> tumults and inſurrections againſt the Goſpel of Chriſt, becauſe it laid the magnificence of their great Goddeſſe in the duſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, men that exalt fleſhly righteouſnes, making a faire ſhew in the fleſh, glorying in their duties, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal conformity,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.</note> and qualifications, as if by their actings they could do ſomething in order to their ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification and ſalvation, are much offended at the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117709:12"/>preaching of the righteouſneſſe of faith, the glory whereof did cauſe the righteouſneſſe of <hi>Ephraim</hi> to vaniſh like a morning cloud, or like an earthly dew. The <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> men zealous of the Law,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.</note> were great adverſaries againſt the Goſpel, and many of Chriſts hearers were offended, &amp; turn'd their backs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his doctrin when he exalted the Fathers free grace and power in the dethroning of the creatures free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will and ability.<note place="margin">John 6.6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> No man (ſaith Chriſt) can come to me except my Father draw him, or except it be given unto him of my Father: Upon this many of his diſciples went away, and walked no more with Jeſus; this was an hard ſaying, they could not beare it. Oh nothing doth ſo ſtumble nature as that which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth nature: they exalted themſelves in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of a power, will, abilitie by nature to come to God, and to life and ſalvation by God: and now to have the glory of al theſe blaſted, for no truth doth ſo diſcover the inability of the creature as this, that no man can come to Chriſt except it be given unto him of the Father, it bringeth down high thoughts of our ſelves, or any thing in our ſelves; therefore ſaid they among themſelves, this is a hard ſaying, what? are we nothing? have we of our ſelves nothing? and can we do nothing? Upon this many departed, and made a receſſe from Chriſt, they walked no more with Jeſus: thus you ſee the ground and reaſon, of all oppoſition againſt the Goſpel: it overſhadoweth and out ſhineth all other glory.</p>
            <p>Now people may manifeſt their enmity and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition againſt the Goſpel either by a fleeing hatred, or by a purſuing hatred, now the goſpel is hated
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117709:13"/>both theſe waies becauſe it outſhineth all other glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. The Papiſts and others did hate it with a purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hatred when they hunted after the blood of the Saints and Martyrs of Jeſus; but (bleſſed be our God) they are now under the hatches who a long time ſat at the ſtern; for God hath made you Honourable Senatours,<note place="margin">Cant. 2.15.</note> in ſtruments to chain up thoſe Foxes who preyed upon the Lambs of Chriſt, and the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite your love into your boſomes, that we can have a palce to reſt our heads, and ſet our feet upon, in the Land of our Nativity. We wiſh you well in the name of the Lord, &amp; we remember you in our addreſſes to the Thron e of grace, that God would ſtand by you &amp; be your glory, and your ſtrength: therefore rouze up your ſpirits like men that have God with you and for you, and take courage to ſuppreſſe that bloody and turbulent ſpirit of perſecution that fils the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth with ſo much combuſtion and diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; that you may not reſt untill you have baniſhed it out of your dominions,<note place="margin">Iſaiah 11.6. Iſaiah 65.25. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note> that ſo a more quiet and peaceable ſpirit may dwel with the lamb, and the child may play upon the hole of the Aſp, and there may be no devouring beaſt in all the Lords holy mountain.</p>
            <p>Secondly, enmity againſt the Goſpel is manifeſted by a fleeing hatred: if you obſerve the enemies, and ſecret Antipathies, among the creatures, you ſhal ſee weak creature, flee from thoſe creatures that are offenſive to their nature, if they cannot over-power them:<note place="margin">qui mali aget odit lucem.</note> ſo when men are not able to hinder the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth of the light of truth, they ſhun it, and wil not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117709:13"/>come unto it. In the ſecond of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> this fl eing hatred is fully ſet forth, the whole Chapter ſpeaketh of the downfall of the glory, power &amp;c. of man,<note place="margin">Iſaiah 2. chap</note> yea all Idols ſhal utterly be aboliſhed verſe, 20. Yea ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſhal they be to looke the light in the face, or lift their head, before the wiſdome and truth of God; that at the, 21. verſe they ſhall go into the holes of the rocks and caves of the earth, that is, into darke and Subterreanean places; ſo offenſive is the light unto them, ſo unable are they to endure the luſtre,<note place="margin">Iſaiah 2.21.</note> glory and Majeſtie of the Lord; which are ſo deſtructive to corrupt and carnal wayes, that they creep into the clefts of the rocks, and holes of the ragged rocks, for fear of the Lord and glory of his Majeſty: The words ſeem to be an alluſion unto the uſuall cuſtome of thoſe feeble creatures, who when they are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to deal with creatures ſtronger then themſelves, who would deſtroy them; they retire into ſuch places, where they may beſt pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ect themſelves from the power of their antagoniſts: as coneys wil get into their boroughs for fear of the doggs; thus ment when they cannot endure the pure and powerful preaching of the Goſpel in the place where they live, it doth caſt ſuch contempt and ſhame upon them and all their wayes, they wil get into the darke places of the land, even into the borders of <hi>Zebulon</hi> and <hi>Neph-thali,</hi> the Regions and ſhadowe; of death, where people periſh for want of knowledge; that ſo they may there ſettle themſelves upon the ſtool of tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and preſerve their carnall worſhip and wayes from being blaſted and overſhadowed by the glory of the Goſpel. Thus men oppoſe and hate the Goſpel, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117709:14"/>it outſhineth all other glory, and they hate it ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a purſuing hatred,<note place="margin">Revel. 22.15.</note> as doggs (for ſo the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture calleth them) barking at the people of God and waies of Chriſt, yea which is worſe, they will bite alſo, and that when they do not barke, crying peace, peace, and yet bite with the teeth: as the Prophet ſaith like thoſe doggs we read of in a ſtrange land; that barkewhen the Sun riſeth, or like the doggs here with us: that fall a barking when the Moon ſhineth; thus many fret and fume, vex, perplex and torment them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves when the Sun of righteouſnes ariſeth with heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his wings,<note place="margin">Mal. 4.2.</note> ſhineth forth upon the ſouls of Saints with beams of light and refreſhment. But the Sun whichmelteth wax, doth harden clay, for that which is our comfort, poor wretches it is their torment; and you ſee alſo they hate the Goſpel with a fleeing hatred, like Bats and Owls, who cannot abide the light, retire into holes and thickets, and like ſome beaſts get into their dens when the Sun and light break forth, they go into the caves of the earth and the clefts of the rocks for fear of the Lord and the glory of his Majeſty, when he ariſeth, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If the Glory of Chriſtdoth outſhine al other glories that ſtand up in competition withit,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> then Honourable Senatours, ſet not up any earthly glory in competition with Chriſt, for it will be darkened and overſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. We ſet up gifts in competition with Chriſt, when we admire them, and not Chriſt the author, &amp; donor of them, when we attribute more to them, then to the grace of God; we ſet up humane wiſdome in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition with Chriſt, when we make it abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the diſpenſation of the Goſpel, yea ſuch
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117709:14"/>an eſſentiall qualification, as if without it none could be inabled for the holding forth the word of life: now this doth detract from the alfufficiency of Chriſt,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.9.</note> as if he could not furniſh his Saints with the tongue of the learned to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon to thoſe that are weary without acquired arts and Sciences: I do not ſpeak againſt gifts and learning, they are excellent ornements unto nature, and (for ought I know unto grace alſo, for the gold did beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the Temple, though the Temple did Sanctifie the gold; but I ſpeak againſt the axalting them before Chriſt you know a candle is of good uſe in a darkeroome, but when you light it up before the Sun, it is outſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and made uſeleſs. God maketh fooliſhneſſe the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of this world, confoundeth the underſtanding of the prudent, and doth deſtroy and blaſt the glory of all humane excellencies; yea doth powre contempt upon them when they exalt themſelves before him: therefore if Chriſt doth begin to overſhadow theſe creature-glories, let's not crie them up for though we ſhould never ſo endeavour to quicken the admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them in the hearts of men; yet we ſhall not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to keep up their eſteem, and preſerve their glory when they begin to die and fade, the ſpirit of the Lord blowing upon them. We have had experience of this,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 5.2.</note> for we ſet up the Dagon of mans invented worſhip be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Arke of God, but the power and Majeſty of the truth of God made him lick the duſt, for down he tumbled before the Arke, and though the hand of God was exceedingly againſt us in this deſinge, yet ſuch was our blind zeal, that we would not deſiſt, but lent Dagon our hand again, and gave him the other lift, and helped him into his ſeat again; yea we faſted for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117709:15"/>him, and prayed for him until we had ſet him up, but in the morning this <hi>Dagon</hi> was fallen unto the earth again, and had broke his neck and hands, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the ſtump of <hi>Dagon</hi> remaines, for nothing doth ſo deface and deform mans worſhip as the light of truth ſhining forth.</p>
            <p>Truely we would have healed <hi>Babylon</hi> but ſhe would not be healed, even let us give her over as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable. And honourable Senators,<note place="margin">1 Kings 18.</note> if <hi>Baal</hi> be a god let him plead for himſelf, lend him your power no more, for he layeth claim to a <hi>Jus Divinum,</hi> now if he be (as he pretends) of the ſtock and linage of <hi>David,</hi> if he be as <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſme) from heaven, he is armed from heaven, and ſtrengthened with a divine power againſt all wayes that do oppoſe him, and therefore need not be afraid to looke the light in the face, or lift up his head before the Arke. Alſo let's not ſet up humane power in competition with Chriſt, let's not depend upon it as if a man could be delivered by much ſtrength, let's not glory as if our hil were made ſo ſtrong, that it could never be moved when the arm of fleſh is with us; but eſpecially take heed of ſetting up humane power againſt Chriſt, leaſt it be broken like a potters veſſel. You have ſeen theſe powers of the beaſt and Dagon fall before the Arke, and if <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai</hi> be of the ſeed of the <hi>Jews</hi> before whom <hi>Hamon</hi> hath begun to fall,<note place="margin">Eſther 6.13.</note> he will fall and riſe no more. Oh let all proud <hi>Hamans</hi> ceaſe perſecuting poor <hi>Morde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cai,</hi> leaſt they bring an <hi>odium</hi> upon themſelves before the Lord, for let them engage their wiſdome, power and greatneſſe againſt the wayes of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Magna eſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas &amp; prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valet.</note> the power of Chriſt, even in babes and ſucklings, perſons mean
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117709:15"/>and contemptible, will bear them down before it;<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.2.</note> for great is the Lord, and his glory doth out-ſhine all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther glories.</p>
            <p>If we would not be troubled at the breaking forth of the light and glory of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> let's be willing this bright cloud ſhould overſhadow us, willing to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſed and decreaſe,<note place="margin">John 3.30.</note> that Chriſt may be exalted and encreaſe. Beloved, I do diſcover the cloud ariſing, and it wil overſhadow us, for though for preſent it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth about the bigneſſe of a mans hand,<note place="margin">1 Kings 18.45.</note> it will encreaſe until it overſpread the heaven, and darken al the glory of man. Beloved, if my Aſtrologie fail not, the glory of fleſh wil ſuffer a great eclips,<note place="margin">Iſay 40.6.</note> and it wil be viſible with us if the aire be cleare: indeed for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it is ſomewhat darkened with the ſmoke of the bottomleſſe pit,<note place="margin">Rev. 9.3.</note> but there is hope that darkneſſe wil be diſpelled with the beames of the Sun of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe;<note place="margin">Mal. 4.</note> now this prognoſtication though calculated properly for <hi>England,</hi> yet it may ſerve indifferently for the whole world; for all the Nations round about us, though they be ſtout and lofty, muſt bring their glory unto him who is to be all in all.<note place="margin">Rev. 21.26.</note> This predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is grounded upon that 24 of <hi>Matthew,</hi> which place though underſtood of Chriſts laſt coming,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.29.</note> yet is true alſo of his coming in the miniſtry of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, which doth darken the Sun, Moon and Stars; all theſe inferior luminaries of earthly glory wax pale and dim, when the Son of man appeareth in his glory: but although the Moon of earthly glory (which is ſubject to encreaſe and wane and many changes) be thus eclipſed, yet our glorious Sun ſhal never be eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117709:16"/>from the ſoul of his people; yea it ſhall never go down,<note place="margin">Iſay 60.19.</note> for the Lord ſhal be their everlaſting light, and God their glory, but from others it will be eclipſed; there may be an interpoſition of thick clouds, and darkneſſe being upon them, they cannot ſee the King in his beauty,<note place="margin">Jer. 17.5.</note> or as it is in, <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 17. they ſhall not ſee good when it cometh,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.25.</note> the grace, love, glory, and goodneſs of God in Chriſt ſhall be hidden from them; or the Devil may interpoſe the body of the earth betwixt their ſouls and the Sun of righteouſneſſe, and ſo depriv them of the joy and comfort of his enliven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and in lightening influence.<note place="margin">Mal. 4.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore to conclude: your oppoſition will be againſt the Goſpel, if your glory and life be hid in creatures, becauſe your very life is deſtroyed when creature-glory is overſhadowed, if you live and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in things below the Lord Jeſus,<note place="margin">Mat. 2.3.</note> with <hi>Herod,</hi> you will be troubled to hear of a Chriſt, with thoſe in the <hi>Revelations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 16.10.</note> you will be found to gnaw your tongues for paine, and blaſpheme the God of heaven becauſe of the prevailing power of truth, and break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth of Goſpel-light; and with the Merchants of <hi>Babylon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 18.16.</note> to weep and waile, crying, Alas, alas, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the downfal of the Kingdome of the Beaſt: But if your life be hid with Chriſt in God,<note place="margin">Col. 3.3.</note> you will rejoyce when he appeareth: and you will be found in the number of thoſe that did ſhout untill the earth rang againe, when the Arke came into the Camp of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 4.5. Rev. 19.1.</note> or of thoſe that cry Hallelujah, Hallelujah, for the Lord rejoyceth: So welcome will the appearance of Chriſt in his Goſpel be unto your ſoules, that this
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117709:16"/>will be your joyful acclamation:<note place="margin">John 12.13</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is he that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the name of the Lord, Hoſanna to the Son of David.</hi> Chriſtians, ſtudy theſe truths, I leave them with you, and I commend you to the grace and goodneſs of our Redeemer.<note place="margin">Luke 19.38,</note>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
